I have about 40 medical health nutrition
journals that send me their daily and
weekly releases of studies and I'll take
a quick look at what releases to see if
there's anything especially interesting
or helpful to share here. Well, on one
particular day in January, January 28th
to be specific, three clinical trials
released showing a burgeoning frontier
of health can dramatically help combat
cancer. What I found intriguing is that
these studies come from separate labs,
yet they were very close in their design
and outcomes that they were interested
in, which made this combined release all
that more impactful, especially as they
looked at different forms of cancer from
skin cancer to lung cancer to kidney
cancer. Anyway, one of the major issues
in cancer is this dance between cancer
cells and your immune cells that hinges
on a receptor found on your immune cells
called PD1. Essentially, some immune
cells, especially specialized ones like
cytotoxic tea cells, are like rabid dogs
fletching their teeth at anything that
looks out of the ordinary. So they come
with this PD1 receptor on their membrane
that when bound inactivates the T- cell,
keeping it from attacking and
destroying. It turns out that successful
cancer cells have the binding protein
that binds to PD1 called PDL1.
So when TE-C cells get close to the
cancer cell, the cancer cell just
engages with the PD1 receptor using its
PDL1 protein and inactivates the TE-C
cell. a lot like playing a harp for
Fluffy on the third floor of Hogwarts
castle. Let me know if you understood
that reference. Now, one of the major
therapies that we use in medicine is to
use imunotherapy, which strongly favors
the dance towards TE-C cells unfettered
attacks on cancer. Essentially,
amunotherapies will bind the cancer's
PDL1 protein and therefore block it from
interacting with the T- cells PD1
receptor, therefore keeping TE-C cells
active and attacking. There are
different versions, but that's the
common one. Now, I'm pointing all this
out, but that's not because this is the
frontier of health. It's to bring your
attention to the interplay and heavy
dependence of your body to be able to
fight against cancer through a strong
immune system. What these clinical
trials show is that to support our
immune system and supercharge its
ability to fight cancer, we should turn
our attention to our gut. Not
necessarily the cells that make up our
gut, the epithelial cells, but the
microbes within our colon, the billions
of them called the microbiome.
Now, in all three of these clinical
trials, participants were given pills
that massively changed their microbiome.
We'll discuss how in just a minute. Now,
a great example is shown in this
randomized control trial called the
Tacito trial where people with cancer
were given the microbiome altering pills
or placebo with amunotherapy like what
we just discussed. Then over the next
several years, their survival from
cancer was quantified. The blue is the
microbiome altered participants and the
red line is the placebo. The lower the
lines fall, the more people died.
Unfortunately, clearly under otherwise
identical conditions, those with changed
microbiome survived way more than those
that are just using the imu the
imunotherapy. In fact, around 80% of
people were still alive after 3 years,
which is impressive. What's even more
impressive is that when researchers just
focused on the data coming from people
with poor prognosis, as in more advanced
forms of cancer, less likely to survive
and so on, they also experience similar
results. So the point here being that if
you improve your microbiome, you are far
more resilient against cancer at least
based on the initial human studies that
pointed out what is an improved
microbiome and what exactly are they
doing to affect cancer on the kidneys or
the lung or elsewhere? Well, as
explained with the PD1 and the PDL1
lethal dance between TE-C cells and
cancer cells respectively, the immune
system is disregulated when fighting
cancer. meaning fewer cancer killing
immune cells are present or they're just
less effective in some way. Now,
apparently improvements in the
microbiome lead to resurgence of cancer
killing cells, especially a type of
immune cell whispered in the back alleys
of your body with a twinge of fear
called the natural killer cell. So more
and more active NK cells leads to larger
specialized force invading into the
tumors and destroying the cancer cells
left and right. My point here is that we
have early signs that the immune system
becomes more robust when the microbiome
improves thereby allowing the immune
system better attacks against cancer.
All right. So where does this all take
us? What can be done? dayto day. Well,
that's what we'll get into. And if
you're looking for more depth, like more
on a protein called DNA1 and the
relationship to cancer or particular
bacteria found to track with worse or
better cancer outcomes based on these
studies and more, then check out the
extended edition of this video that
you're watching. It's included along
with an article, podcast, live sessions
with me, physionic AI, and more. as a
member of the Physionic Insiders. You
can join via the link in the
description. I hope to speak with you
there. Here's the thing. Maybe in the
future, these will become widely
available, but the pills that these
people consumed were poop pills
containing the microbiome of other
healthy people without cancer or people
with cancer that had excellent responses
to imunotherapy. I mean, think about it
for a second. The only thing separating
other people's poop from your mouth is
an extremely thin capsule shell and you
have to consume about 20 of them.
Well, anyway, that might be an option in
the future, but we have other options
right now shown in this diagram that
came off of one of the studies. We're
looking at a mixture of future
treatments and current options. The top
is a version of what was done in the
study, but we'd like to move from
consuming poop tablets. So, from left to
right, from most accessible to least, at
the moment at least, we have nutritional
interventions of which prebiotics are a
favorite. Think fibers for example. Or
moving on to supplementation like the
fats that are produced by our microbes
in our gut called shortchain fats. Then
we get into more medical technology like
bacteriaop phasages which are honestly
an incredibly innovative approach to
changing our microbiome that I can get
into in the future if you're interested.
And then finally an even more
personalized medicine based on samples
of microbiome showing poor micro number.
Another important point to keep in mind
is that many studies look at the
microbiome and health focus on something
called the Shannon index, which measures
the microbiome diversity. There's
definitely more to the microbiome than
just diversity. Typically, most studies
indicate that greater microbiome
diversity is associated with better
health outcomes, but in these studies,
while some did indicate the same, others
didn't. The reason is because we're
early in understanding an ideal
microbiome in relation to cancer. In
fact, to confuse things further, the
loss of microbes seem to play more
impactful role than adding species of
microbes shown here. Better outcomes
came from some new microbes sticking
around. So, i.e. grafting in grafting
and the majority of the effect of
changing the microbiome for the better
was purging the gut of microbes shown in
the lost not to be distracted by the
2000's show. So a lot of questions and
although we have three clinical trials
they're small with only one having
proper control group since these were
like phase one and phase two clinical
trials still this offers us three
lessons. So one, our m our understanding
of the microbiome in relation to cancer
is in its infancy. But an improved
microbiome taken from people with proven
highquality microbiome due to their
ability to fight cancer leads to big
improvements in fighting cancer. There
is a gut connection here that needs to
be explored. Number two, greater
microbiome diversity. Purging particular
bad bacteria and adding good bacteria.
We aren't entirely sure what the trick
is, but there's some mixture of those
that creates an ideal microbiome for
fighting cancer. And three, while poop
pills are not widely available yet, they
are an easy solution for the future.
Until then, the researchers argue for
more prebiotics like fiber and possibly
more metabolites like short- chain fats.
And speaking to both of those, I think
they have a strong point overall because
I've covered a ton of fascinating
research describing far more details on
both of those right here and right here.
Microbiome research has really picked up
steam. These three studies firmly
identified that and I hope to cover more
in the future. Thanks for hanging out.
I'll catch you in the next one. See you.